Wyoming Conference United Methodist Church Records
Wyoming Conference United Methodist Church Records
1806-1979
United Methodist Church. Wyoming Conference.
14 linear feet
Business files (minutes, financial records, hearing records, circuit records, school and missionary society records of individual churches of the Conference); correspondence; memorabilia; and printed material.
148770
Biographical History
The Wyoming Conference of the United Methodist Church is an umbrella organization that connects more than 300 United Methodist congregations (with more than 60,000 individual members) in Northeastern Pennsylvania and the Southern Tier of New York State. The Wyoming Conference's mission is "to assist local churches in making disciples for Christ, so as to transform the world."
The first Wyoming Conference was held in Carbondale, Pennsylvania, in 1852. Two notable outgrowths of the Wyoming Conference are the Children's Home of Wyoming Conference, focused on needs of and service to children, and United Methodist Homes, whose mission revolves around needs of and service to the aged. The Conference is are also affiliated with Wyoming Seminary, one of the oldest continuously coeducational day and boarding schools in the United States.
[Portions of this biographical sketch adapted from the Wyoming Conference website at http://www.wyomingconference.org.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Wyoming Conference of the United Methodist Church Records contain business files, correspondence, memorabilia and printed material relating to the Wyoming Conference organization of United Methodist congregations.
Business files relates to the Wyoming Conference itself as well as to individual member churches. Types of material include both general administrative material (constitution and by-laws, anniversary publications, meeting minutes, speeches and addresses, etc.) and financial records (check stubs, bills, receipts, etc).
General Correspondence covers more than 130 years.
Assorted items of Memorabilia include photographs, scrapbooks, maps, posters, and other miscellanea.
Printed material includes Conference newsletters, historical studies, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, and assorted other items.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically; all other series are alphabetical by name or topic.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; New York State; Religion and philosophy; United Methodist Church. -- Wyoming Conference. -- Archives.; United Methodist Church (U.S.); Methodist Church -- Clergy.; Methodist Church -- New York (State); Methodist Church -- Pennsylvania.; Correspondence.; Financial reports.; Minutes (administrative records); Photoprints.; Clergy.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Three folders of Board of Ministry Records business files are restricted.
Inventory
- Business files
  - Adelphian Society Records, 1866-1901; 1910-1930; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Asbury United Methodist Church 100th Anniversary, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Autobiography of H. E. Daniels, 1889 (Box 1)
  - Binghamton and Vicinity Methodist Ministers' Association
    - [General], 1923-1933; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - [General], 1933-1959; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Receipted bills, 1908-1912 (Box 2)
    - Records, 1894-1913 (Box 2)
  - Binghamton District Ministerial and Literary Association
    - Receipted bills, 1908-1912 (Box 2)
    - Records, 1894-1913 (Box 2)
  - Biography of Thomas H. Pearne, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Board of Ministry Records, 1942-1968; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Broad Street Church, 1973; preacher and pastor list (Box 4)
  - Centenary Church (Syracuse, NY), booklet (Box 4)
  - Central United Methodist Church, 1976-1977 (Box 4)
  - Charles Wesley Brotherhood, 1897; constitution and bylaws (Box 4)
  - Children's Home of Wyoming Conference, 1973; 60th anniversary bulletin (Box 4)
  - Church Extension Anniversary, 1898 (Box 4)
  - Church Extension Society Records, 1869-1878 (Box 4)
  - Commission on Archives and History, 1971-1972; minutes (Box 4)
  - Committee reports, 1964-1972 (Box 4)
  - Conference Program Council Forward Planning Committee, 1969; report (Box 5)
  - Constitution of the Binghamton District Ministerial Association, 1894-1912 (Box 5)
  - Educational Institutions Study Committee, 1970; report (Box 5)
  - Epworth League Records, 1896-1924 (Box 5)
  - Evidence concerning case of George T. Price, 1899 (Box 5)
  - Financial records
    - Archives and History treasurer's report and budget, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - Budget manuals, 1968-1972 (Box 5)
    - Cancelled checks and statements, 1945-1950 (Box 5)
    - Capital funds study, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Checks, 1893-1895 (Box 5)
    - Check stubs, 1943-1968; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - General, 1963-1972; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Idetown United Methodist Church, 1961-1975 (Box 7)
    - Paid bills, 1946-1961 (Box 7)
    - Preacher's Aid Fund records, 1916-1936 (Box 7)
    - Receipts, 1947-1958 (Box 7)
    - Wyoming Conference Camp Commission
      - Cancelled checks, 1945-1949 (Box 7)
      - Paid bills, 1945-1948 (Box 7)
      - Statements, 1946 (Box 7)
  - Financial reports, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Financial reports (cont.) (Box 8)
  - First Wyoming Conference representative meeting, 1894; minutes (Box 8)
  - Fragments (Box 8)
  - Glen Lyon Church, 1974; history (Box 8)
  - Glen Lyon Methodist Church, 1973; 85th anniversary bulletin (Box 8)
  - Gospel Music Museum, 1977; dedication (Box 8)
  - Hanover Circuit of Susquehanna District Records, 1843-1860 (Box 8)
  - Hearing records concerning Rev. Van Valkenburg, 1865 (Box 8)
  - Historical address for Wyoming Annual Conference Historical Society, 1899 (Box 8)
  - Historical sketch of Oneonta District ministerial meeting, 1929 (Box 8)
  - Historical speech, 1931 (Box 8)
  - Historic sketch of the Binghamton District Ministerial and Literary Association, 1912 (Box 8)
  - History of Methodism in Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania, 1892 (Box 8)
  - History of the "Master's Call" program (Box 8)
  - Horresdale District Conference Records, 1873-1878 (Oversize 1)
  - Huntsville United Methodist Church, 1977; 100th anniversary (Box 8)
  - Idetown Administrative Board, 1977; agenda (Box 8)
  - Insurance papers, 1970 (Box 8)
  - Journal of the Traveling and Local Preachers' Mutual Improvement Society of the Susquehanna District, 1842-1872 (Box 8)
  - Kingston, Pennsylvania Quarterly Conference minutes, 1889-1914 (Box 8)
  - Ladies Aid Society Records, 1914-1921 (Box 8)
  - Ladies Aid Society secretary's book, 1898-1914 (Box 9)
  - Map of Methodism in the Southern States, 1898 (Box 9)
  - Methodist Home for the Aged, 1969; financial reports (Box 9)
  - Methodist Ministers' Association of Scranton Records, 1906-1921; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Methodist Ministers' Association of Wilkes-Barre and Vicinity, 1942-1947 (Box 9)
  - Methodist Quarterly Review, 1867 (Box 9)
  - Ministerial Association Records, 1910-1942 (Box 10)
  - Minutes of the Western New York Conference of the Methodist Episcopal Church, 1873 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 1898-1945 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous history, 1896 (Box 10)
  - Newport Circuit Records (Box 10)
  - North Abington Charge Records (Oversize 2)
  - Notebook, handwritten (Box 10)
  - Oak Street United Methodist Church Records, 1971-1976 (Box 10)
  - Owego District Ministerial Association, 1848-1877; minutes (Box 10)
  - "The Pleasures of Sin" by John D. Sasson, 1845; handwritten; appears to be sermon (Box 11)
  - Programs, 1927-1961 (Box 11)
  - Properties Study of the Wyoming Conference, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Quarterly tickets, 1835-1889 (Box 11)
  - Record of pastoral work of J. T. Warner, 1868-1924; 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Report of the Council on World Service and Finance, 1964; 1968; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - School of Missions, 1971; undated (Box 11)
  - School of Missions, 1973-1974; undated (Box 12)
  - Steward's Book (Box 12)
  - Tour itineraries, 1976 (Box 12)
  - Trucksville Church History (Box 12)
  - United Methodist Conference daily bulletin, 1976 (Box 12)
  - [Untitled records], 1806-1900 (Box 12)
  - Vacationland Ministries report, 1967 (Box 12)
  - Whittemore Hill Church anniversary, 1977-1978 (Box 12)
  - Wilkes-Barre Methodist Ministers' Association Records (Box 12)
  - Wilkes-Barre Preachers' Meeting Constitution, 1891-1924 (Box 13)
  - Will of William H. Olin (Box 13)
  - Women's Missionary Society secretary's records, 1924-1932 (Box 13)
  - Wyalusing District Ministerial Association Records, 1871-1877 (Box 13)
  - Wyoming Circuit church register, 1814-1848 (Box 13)
  - Wyoming Conference
    - Anniversary Celebration pageant script (Box 13)
    - Historical record, 1962 (Box 13)
    - Journal, 1885-1888 (Oversize 2)
    - Records, miscellaneous, 1964-1979 (Box 13)
    - Structure Committee minutes, 1972 (Box 13)
    - Union Committee records, 1971-1972 (Box 13)
  - Wyoming District
    - Annual Conference Committee on Conference Relations records, 1929-1954 (Box 14)
    - Epworth League Institute Commission, 1936-1950 (Box 14)
    - Lyceum records, 1843-1963 (Box 14)
    - Ministerial Association records, 1889-1910 (Box 15)
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1844-1859; 1852-1859,; 1891-1898,; 1910-1911,; 1928,; 1945-1947,; 1950-1965; 12 folders (Box 15)
  - [General], 1966-1978; 2 folders (Box 16)
- Memorabilia
  - "Bishops of the Methodist Episcopal Church", 19th c. (Oversize 3)
  - Cane (Oversize 4)
  - Etching blocks
    - Wilton J. Dubrick (Box 16)
    - Sky Lake camp scenes (Box 16)
    - Sky Lake directors (Box 16)
    - J. T. Warner (Box 16)
  - Gavels and block, 3 items (Oversize 3)
  - Map of Wyoming Conference (Box 16)
  - Missionary Society Certificate, 1865 (Oversize 5)
  - Photographs (Box 16)
  - Photographs, 1875; 1890,; 1913; conferences and convertions at Oneonta, NY; Binghamton, NY; Wilkes-Barre, PA (Oversize 5)
  - Portrait of William Lord Conyngham II (Oversize 6)
  - Scrapbook of photographs (Box 17)
  - Walkathon poster (Box 17)
  - The Wesley Oak (Box 17)
  - Wyoming Conference Centennial Fund certificate, 1884 (Oversize 5)
- Printed material
  - Booklets
    - A history of Nichols, N.Y. (Box 17)
    - Dimock Camp Meeting, 1976 (Box 17)
    - The McKendree United Methodist Church 150th Anniversary, 1978 (Box 17)
    - What's Happening, 1978 (Box 17)
  - Castle Creek - Glen Castle Church Bulletin, 1976 (Box 17)
  - Centennial Pageant of Wyoming Conference Program, 1952 (Box 17)
  - Conference newsletter, 1978 (Box 17)
  - Congressional Record, 1960 (Box 17)
  - Court Street United Methodist Church 100th Anniversary, 1976 (Box 17)
  - Daily Christian Advocate, 1916 (Oversize 6)
  - Health and Welfare Certification Council brochure (Box 17)
  - Hinghwa, 1923 (Box 17)
  - Invitations, 1892-1942 (Box 17)
  - Newspaper, The Beacon, 1978 (Box 17)
  - Newspaper, The Press (Binghamton ), 1978 (Oversize 6)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1972 (Box 17)
  - Newspaper reprint, 1902 (Box 17)
  - The Northeastern United Methodist Historical Bulletin, 1967-1978 (Box 17)
  - Pamphlets
    - "How to Display and Respect the Flag of the United States" (Box 17)
    - Lackawanna Historical Society (Box 17)
    - North Afton United Methodist Church 150 Years, 1978 (Box 17)
    - Union Valley United Methodist Church 125th Anniversary, 1978 (Box 17)
  - Poster, advertising The Young Lady's Book by William Hosmer, 1851 (Oversize 6)
  - Sixth Northeastern Jurisdictional Conference, 1960 (Box 17)